<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King a proclamation for restraint of killing, dressing, and eating of flesh in Lent, or on fish-dayes, appointed by the law, to be hereafter strictly obserued by all sorts of people.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8850</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3550</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33150414</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33150414</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28594</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22432)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28594)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1876:82)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King a proclamation for restraint of killing, dressing, and eating of flesh in Lent, or on fish-dayes, appointed by the law, to be hereafter strictly obserued by all sorts of people.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3] leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Bonham Norton and Iohn Bill, Printers  to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXVI [1626, i.e. 1627]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Arms with initials "C R" at top. Sheet 3, line 4, has "Our vse".</note>
                  <note>"Giuen at Our Court at Hampton Court, the 25. day of Ianuary, in the second yeere of Our Reigne of Great Britaine, France and Ireland."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lent.</term>
               <term>Meat industry and trade --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Food law and legislation --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:28594:1"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the King. A Proclamation for reſtraint of killing, dreſsing, and eating of Fleſh in Lent, or on Fiſh-dayes, appointed by the Law, to be hereafter obſerued by all ſorts of people.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas diuers good Lawes and Statutes, haue heretofore, with</hi> great care and prouidence been made and enacted for the due obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Lent, and other dayes appointed for Fiſhdayes aſwel for the ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and increaſe of Fleſh victuall, as for the maintenance of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie &amp; Shipping of this Realme, by the encouragement of Fiſhermen to goe to the Seas for the taking of Fiſh, which Lawes, and politique Conſtitutions, haue from time to time been ſeconded and quickened by ſundry Proclamations, and other Acts and Ordinances of State in the tunes of Our Royall Predeceſſors; And whereas, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo many good prouiſions heretofore had and made in that kinde, We haue obſerued, that the inordinate libertie vſually taken by all ſorts of people, to kill, dreſſe and cate Fleſh in the Lent ſeaſon, and on other dayes and times prohibited, is become ſo inueterate an euill, that it will require more then ordinary care to ſuppreſſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>We therefore, much affecting the reformation of ſo great and growing an euil, which is ſo great an enemie to the plenty of this Our Kingdome, Haue thought fit thus timely, (the better to take away all pretences of excuſe) to expreſſe Our ſelfe and Our Royall Commandement in this behalfe: Whereof without future declaration of Our pleaſure in this kinde, We ſhall expect, and doe require from all Our Subiects, that due notice be taken, and that a ſtrict and continued obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and conformitie be yeelded thereunto, both for the preſent, and in all ſucceeding times.</p>
            <p>And therefore Wee doe ſtraitly charge and command all and euery perſon and perſons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, to whom it may appertaine, carefully to prouide and ſee, that theſe Orders following may be duely obſerued and put in execution, vpon paine of Our high diſpleaſure, and ſuch penalties, as by the Lawes of this Our Realme may be inflicted vpon the Offenders, for their contempt or neglect of Vs and Our Lawes, whereof Wee ſhall ſhew Our Selfe moſt ſenſible.</p>
            <p>And firſt, whereas we find, that the chiefeſt cauſe of theſe diſorders hath growen from the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences that haue been granted to Butchers to kill and vtter Fleſh contrary to Law, and that by Our Lawes, no Maior, Iuſtice of Peace, or other perſon of what degree or quality ſoeuer, can grant any Licence in this kinde; And that the Lords and others of Our Priuy Councell, doe by Our direction forbeare to grant the ſame, or giue way thereunto; Our will and pleaſure is, vpon the penalties prouided by Law, and ſuch further puniſhment to be inflicted vpon the offenders, as ſhall be thought meete, that no ſuch Licence ſhall be granted for the killing or vttering of Fleſh; And, that no Butcher, or other perſon whatſoeuer, doe by colour thereof; kill, vtter, or put to ſale any Fleſh contrary to the Lawes eſtabliſhed and prouided in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>And for the auoiding of ſuch inconueniences hereafter, Our will &amp; pleaſure is, That the Lord Maior of Our Citie of <hi>London,</hi> and euery other Officer and Iuſtice of Peace, ſhal call before them, and ſend for any of the ſeruants of any Inholders, Victualers, Cooks, Alehouſekeepers, Tauer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and keepers of Ordinary tables, &amp; ſuch others that vtter Victuals, &amp; to examine them vpon their corporall Oathes, what Fleſh is, or hath been during the Lent ſeaſon, or other dayes prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by the Law, dreſſed, killed, vttered, or eaten in their houſes, which if they ſhall refuſe to doe, then to commit to priſon the ſaid ſeruants ſo refuſing vpon their Oaths to declare the trueth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28594:2"/>
            <p>That the Lord Maior ſhall alſo yeerely before Lent, or at the beginning thereof, cauſe all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, keepers of Ordinary tables, Victuallers, Alehouſe keepers, &amp; Tauerners within the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Liberties thereof, to appeare before him, or ſuch perſons as he ſhall appoint meet for that purpoſe; And ſhall take Recognizances with ſufficient Sureties of euery of them in good ſummes of money, <hi>(Viz)</hi> One hundred pounds of the Principal, and their ſureties thirty pounds a piece, to Our vſe, not to dreſſe any Fleſh in their houſes in the Lent time, or at other times prohibited, for any reſpect, nor ſuffer it to be eaten contrary to Law. The like Recognizance with Sureties ſhal be taken of the like parties vpon like penalties by the Iuſtices of Peace of Our City of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and the Liberties thereof, &amp; euery of the ſaid Recognizances to be certified into Our Exchequer.</p>
            <p>And for the Butchers, and others that come with Victuall or Fleſh out of the Countrey into the Citie, Our pleaſure is, That the Lord Maior ſhall cauſe certaine perſons to watch at the Gates and other like places in the Suburbs, where Fleſh may be brought, to view &amp; ſearch, and to intercept the ſame: And if any of thoſe Watchmen ſhall bee found negligent and corrupt in his Charge, then he to be committed to priſon during the whole Lent.</p>
            <p>And to the end that Fiſhermen may imploy themſelues to Sea with better encouragement then heretofore, and that the Fiſhmongers may furniſh themſelues with ſuch ſtore from time to time hereafter, as ſhall be expedient, aſwell for the prouiſion of the Citie, as for ſelling the ſame at reaſonable Rates, We will that they take notice of this Our Commandement &amp; conſtant reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution for obſeruance of Lent, &amp; Fiſh dayes, both now and hereafter, as by Law is required.</p>
            <p>And furthermore, as We thinke it fit, that euery man ſhould be a rule of order and abſtinence in his owne houſe, aſwell in reſpect of the publique, as of his priuate caſe and benefit: So We ſtraitly charge and command all Inholders, keepers of Ordinary tables<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Victuallers, Alehouſe keepers, and Tauerners, not to make any Supper for any perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, vpon Friday nights either in Lent or out of Lent, nor to ſuffer any meate to be then dreſſed vttered, ſold, or ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in their houſes, vpon paine of ſuch puniſhment, as is due to thoſe that ſhall contemne Our Royall pleaſure and Commandement.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as vpon further aduice and conſideration had, that the reſtraint of killing and dreſſing of Fleſh is no ſufficient remedie for the miſchiefe, valeſſe there be better care alſo taken to ſuppreſſe the vnlawfull and inordinate eating of Fleſh in the time of Lent, and on other daies and times prohibited, wherewith our Subiects haue accuſtomed themſelues, rather for delicacie then for neceſſitie, It is therefore our Roall will and pleaſure, and accordingly, We doe hereby ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prohibit and forbid all Our Subiects, of what degree or qualitie ſoeuer within this Realme, to eat any maner of Fleſh in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of Lent, or on other daies now vſually obſerued as Fiſh daies, without a ſpeciall Licence firſt obtained from the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or ſuch other as by the Law haue power to giue Licence in that behalfe, according to Our Lawes in that caſe proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, (which We will and command ſhal be ſparingly granted, and in caſes of neceſſitie onely) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on paine of our High diſpleaſure, and to be proceeded againſt by Our Attourney generall in Our Court of Star chamber, as contemners of Our Royall commandement, and vpon ſuch further penalties, as by the Lawes and Statutes of Our Realme may bee inflicted on thoſe that ſhall wilfully offend in this kinde.</p>
            <p>And as theſe Orders are to be executed in Our Citie of <hi>London,</hi> and places neere to the ſame, ſo it is Our expreſſe pleaſure and Commandement, That our Iuſtices of Peace in all Shires with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their Rule, &amp; all other Maiors, Bailifes and chiefe Officers in Towns Corporate or in any Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties within their Precincts, ſhall cauſe the ſame to be obſerued &amp; performed in like maner; and that no maner of Toleration, Fauour, or Conniuencie be vſed by any Iuſtice of Peace, or other Officer, contrary to the true meaning of this Our Proclamation, as both they that ſhall preſume wittingly ſo to tolerate the offence, as alſo the party himſelfe offending, will anſwere the ſame at their vttermoſt perils; Our Commandement being, That Our Lawes in this caſe ſhall be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſeuerely executed vpon all Offenders whatſoeuer:</p>
            <p>Further charging and Commanding the Lord Maior of Our City of <hi>London,</hi> the Iuſtices of Aſſiſe in their ſeuerall Circuits, the Maiors and the chiefe Officers of all other Cities and Townes Corporate, Iuſtices of Peace, Lords of Liberties, and all other Officers and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters within the ſeuerall Counties of this Our Realme, that they and euery of them fully obey this Our pleaſure, and cauſe and compell the ſame to be obeyed and executed by others, as they will anſwere the contrary at their vttermoſt perils.</p>
            <p>And for the due execution of the premiſſes in all other the Counties of this Our Realme, aſwell as in Our Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> We doe hereby ſtraitly charge and command all Our
<pb facs="tcp:28594:3"/>Iuſtices of Peace within the ſame Counties, aſwell within Liberties as without, That yeerely, and euery yeere hereafter before Lent, they cauſe to come and appeare before them, all Inholders, Cookes, Tauerners, Alehouſe-keepers, Butchers, and others Victuallers whatſoeuer, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire and take of them to Our vſe, ſeuerall Recognizances, with Sureties, for obſeruation of the premiſſes, <hi>(viz.)</hi> The Principals in ten pounds, and their two Sureties in fiue pounds a piece: And if they ſhal refuſe or neglect to enter into ſuch Recognizances, then the ſaid Iuſtices ſhall ſuppreſſe ſuch perſons ſo refuſing, from victualling any more, and ſhall alſo cauſe them forthwith to become bound by Recognizance with Sureties to Our vſe, <hi>(viz.)</hi> The Principals in twenty pounds, and their two Sureties in ten pounds a piece, not to victuall, or ſell Beere or Ale from thencefoorth; which if they ſhall refuſe to doe, then the ſaid Iuſtices to commit to priſon all ſuch perſons ſo refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to enter into ſuch Recognizances, vntill they ſhall ſubmit themſelues, and become bound as aforeſaid. And further, for all ſuch Inholders, Cookes, Tauerners, Alehouſe-keepers, But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and other Victuallers, as ſhall not appeare before the ſaid Iuſtices, as aforeſaid, That they may immediatly ſend forth their Warrants, or grant Proceſſe againſt them, and euery of them ſo making default, to appeare &amp; anſwere their contempt at the next generall Seſſions of the Peace.</p>
            <p>And further, for the more due puniſhment of Inholders, keepers of Ordinary tables, Cookes, Butchers, Victuallers, Alehouſe-keepers, Tauerners, and ſuch like, who ſhall forfeit their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognizances by killing or dreſſing of Fleſh, or ſuffering it to bee eaten in their houſes in the Lent time, and other Fiſh-dayes; And to the end that the ſame may bee as well taken in due forme of Law, as duely certified into Our Exchequer, We doe will and require all Iuſtices of Peace, aſwell within Liberties as without. That at ſuch times as they ſhall meete within their ſeuerall Diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for the taking of ſuch Recognizances, that they giue notice to the Clerks of the Peace, or their deputies, to attend them for that purpoſe; Of whom we will require a ſtrict accompt for the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall taking and returning of the ſame Recognizances into Our ſaid Exchequer.</p>
            <p>And becauſe theſe Directions are for better obſeruation of Order, and due keeping of the Lent according to Our Lawes, which Our Miniſters and Officers are to ſee executed of Office, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making the ſame grieuous to Our People, by taking of exceſſiue Fees for their entring into Recognizances to obſerue theſe Orders, whereof many haue complained: We therefore ſtraite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charge and Command, that no Towne-Clerke, Clerke of the Peace, nor other Officer, ſhall, or doe preſume to demand or take any Fee or Reward aboue the ſumme of twelue pence for taking any ſuch Recognizances as aforeſaid, nor ſhall giue any Fee or Reward for returning the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Our Exchequer.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, for that the Fiſhmongers (vpon the obſeruation of the aforeſaid Orders) may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps take occaſion thereby, to inhaunce the prices, aſwel of Freſh, as of Sea Fiſh, We do therefore hereby further charge and Command al Fiſhmongers whatſoeuer, That they ſell and vtter their Fiſh at moderate and vſuall rates and prices; And that all Iuſtices of Peace, Maiors, Bailiffes, and other Our Officers, aſwell within Liberties as without, to whom it ſhall appertaine, ſhall from time to time take ſuch order with the ſaid Fiſhmongers, that Our Subiects be not grieued by any ſuch enhancement or encreaſe of prices vpon Fiſh, vpon paine of Our high diſpleaſure, and ſuch further puniſhment as may be inflicted vpon them by Our Lawes.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at Our Court at Hampton-Court., <date>the 25. day of Ianuary, in the ſecond yeere of Our Reigne of Great Britaine, France and Ireland.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <closer>God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Bonham Norton and Iohn Bill, Printers to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie. M.DC.XXVI.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
